Guide to the Dillon Anderson papers, 1941-1973 MS 540
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Dillon Anderson papers
1941-1973
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Anderson, Dillon, 1906-1974
MS 540
7 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
Contains materials relating to Anderson's work with Dwight D. Eisenhower as National Security Advisor as well as correspondence and manuscripts related to his short stories, his book Recollections of Eisenhower and book reviews.
Biographical Note
Dillon Anderson (1906-1974) attended Texas Christian University and went on to receive his B.S. from the University of Oklahoma in 1927. He then attended Yale Law School, receiving his L.L.B. in 1929. He became a partner of the law firm Baker Botts of Houston, Texas before serving in World War II. In 1953, he was an official on the National Security Council, before becoming the National Security Advisor in 1955. He also wrote and published numerous short fiction stories, mostly in the 1960s.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, notes, and drafts of Dillon Anderson's book, Recollections of Eisenhower, as well as correspondence with President Eisenhower, notes, and drafts of his speeches, related to his time as National Security Advisor. Series III and IV include Anderson's personal literary works, mainly short stories and articles, and editorial correspondence.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated by Susan Anderson Whiteford, Jill Anderson Kyle and Elizabeth Anderson Martin in 2008, 2009 and 2010.
Index Terms
Subjects
Politics and government; World War (1939-1945); Authors
Document Types
corrrespondence; typescripts
- Series I: Eisenhower research and correspondence, 1952-1973, 239455
  - Recollections of Eisenhower (Vigil Pinkley) 1969-1973 correspondence, 239469 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Eisenhower College - Texas Committee, 239468 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Eisenhower Oral History Project - Columbia University, 239467 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Eisenhower Presidential Library, 239466 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Eisenhower File: Miscellaneous, 239465 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings from 1952 DDE Presidential Campaign, 239464 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - President's Committee to Study US Military Assistance Program 1959, 239463 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Recollections of Eisenhower--Early Drafts, 239462 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Recollections of Eisenhower by Dillon Anderson, 239461 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Republican Presidential Campaign Material 1956, 239460 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Seating of Delegates at Republican National Convention 1952, 239459 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Anderson and Eisenhower Correspondence 1950-1968, 239458 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Eisenhower Correspondence--July 21, 1950-Nov. 3 1952 (first term in office, 239457 (Box 3, Folder 2-4)
  - Eisenhower Correspondence 1953-1956, 239456 (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
- Series II: Speeches, 1950-1972, 239447
  - Speeches given by Dillon Anderson 1950-1960, 239454 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Speeches given by Dillon Anderson 1961-1972, 239453 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Rotary Club Speech April 29, 1965, 239452 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Speech to the South Texas Section of American Institute of Chemical Engineers Feb. 15 1962, 239451 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Speech Material (Data and Notes) [1/3], 239450 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Speech Material (Data and Notes) [2/3], 239449 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Speech Material (Data and Notes) [3/3], 239448 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series III: Writings, 1953-1956 and undated, 239382
  - The Billingsley Papers: Simon and Schuster Publishing Agreement, 239446 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Book Activities and Correspondence 1953-56, 239445 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Book Lists, 239444 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Book Reviews - The Houston Post, 239443 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Drafts, Notes [1/4], 239442 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Drafts, Notes [2/4], 239441 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Drafts, Notes [3/4], 239440 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Drafts, Notes [4/4], 239439 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - General Writings, 239438 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Old Writings/Old Manuscripts, 239437 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Publications- magazine and newspaper articles (about and by) [1/3], 239436 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Publications- magazine and newspaper articles (about and by) [2/3], 239435 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Publications- magazine and newspaper articles (about and by) [3/3], 239434 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Publications of Various Writings, 239433 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Writings - Aegean Cruise piece "Aegean Nightmare", 239432 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Writings - "The Auction" (Claudie), 239431 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Writings - "Be My Host", 239430 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Writings - "Billingsley's Barber", 239429 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Writings - "Billingsley's Bird Dog", 239428 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Writings - "Billingsley and the Empty Saddle", 239427 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Writings - "Billingsley on the Nile", 239426 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Writings - The Billingsley Papers, 239425 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Writings - "Born to Pick Cotton" (Claudie), 239424 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Writings - "A Buffalo Named Woodrow" (Claudie), 239423 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Writings - "Carlsbad's Cavern" (Claudie), 239422 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Writings - "The Carnival" ("The Tunnel of Love") (Claudie), 239421 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Writings - "Chip off the Old Block", 239420 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Writings - "Claudie, Friend of Phlex" (Claudie), 239419 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Writings - "Claudie's Cosmic Vibrations" (Claudie), 239418 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Writings - "The Compleat Billingsley", 239417 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Writings - "The Decision", 239416 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Writings - "The Delegate" (Claudie), 239415 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Writings - "Five Pillars" (Claudie), 239414 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Writings - "Fore, Please, Mr. Billingsley Shooting!", 239413 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Writings - "Forty years of Firewood" (Claudie), 239412 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Writings - "The Good Lord and Mother Nature" (Claudie), 239411 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Writings - "The Green Case" (Hetty Green and Col. Green) Notes, 239410 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Writings - "Herbert will be remembered" (with Robert Bowie), 239409 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Writings - "The Honorable Richard K. Billingsley", 239408 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Writings - "Horace Q. Ball for Governor" (Claudie), 239407 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Writings - "I and Claudie" (Television) Twentieth Century Fox, 239406 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Writings - "Indeed There is a Mrs. Billingsley", 239405 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Writings - "Jolly Good Fellow", 239404 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Writings - "The Lavaliere" (Claudie), 239403 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Writings- "A Little Birthday Music, Please" (Claudie), 239402 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Writings - "The Meanest Man in Washington County" (Claudie), 239401 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Writings - "Morning After", 239400 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Writings - "Mr. United States" (with Robert Bowie), 239399 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Writings - "Never Start a Rumor" (Claudie), 239398 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Writings - "A Quilt for Claudie" (Claudie), 239397 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Writings - "The Receiver" (Claudie), 239396 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Writings - "The Revival" (Claudie), 239395 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Writings - "Sam the Management" (Claudie), 239394 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Writings - "Say More (Pleased to Meet You)", 239393 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Writings - "Secretary to Richard K. Billingsley", 239392 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Writings - "Texas" Articles, 239391 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Writings - "To Hell With Hofuf" (Anderson's Last Short Story) (Claudie), 239390 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Writings - "A Touch of Destiny", 239389 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Writings - "A Town in Very Fine Print" (Claudie), 239388 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Writings - "Turtles Galore" (Claudie), 239387 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Writings - "The Weather Report" (Claudie), 239386 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Writings - "The Windmill Fixers" (short story and script) (Claudie), 239385 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Writings - "When Billingsley Was Young", 239384 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Writings - "You Name It; I'll Drop It" (under pseudonym Lon Anders), 239383 (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Editorial and literary correspondence, 1959-1970, 239369
  - Ruth Aley Correspondence (1962-1963), 239381 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - The Atlantic Monthly, Correspondence, 239380 (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
  - Collier's Correspondence, 239379 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Complimentary Correspondence, 239378 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Editors, 239377 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 239376 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Publishers and Agents Correspondence, 239375 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - Simon and Schuster Publishing Correspondence, 239374 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Daniel Winkler (agent) 1959-1962, 239373 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Daniel Winkler (agent) 1963-1970, 239372 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Mr. Winkler Re: Sheldon Leonard Contract, 239371 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Mrs. Jean Winkler Re: D.A. Books, 239370 (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Series V: Personal WWII materials, 1941-1961, 239361
  - World War II Papers, Dillon Anderson, Col. G.S.C.: Vol. 1: Authority of military commanders; universal military training, 239368 (Box 11)
  - World War II Papers, Dillon Anderson, Col. G.S.C.: Vol. 2: War contracts; law and policy pamphlets, 239367 (Box 11)
  - World War II Papers, Dillon Anderson, Col. G.S.C.: Vol. 3: War contracts; price escalation; labor laws; 48-hour week; first War Powers Act, 239366 (Box 11)
  - World War II Papers, Dillon Anderson, Col. G.S.C.: Vol. 4: War contracts; renegotiation in Army Service Forces, 239365 (Box 11)
  - White House Staff Book 1953-61, No. 83, 239364 (Box 11)
  - Conference of Heads of State of Government, Geneva, Switzerland, July 18 to 23, 1955, 239363 (Box 11)
  - Oversize photo: Unidentified persons, President Eisenhower, Secretary of State John Foster Dulles, Dillon Anderson (in Oval Office), n.d., 239362 (Map-drawer 34)
- Series VI: Writings (addendum), 1949-1961, 239319
  - Published works: The Billingsley Papers, 1961, 239360 (Box 12)
  - Published works: I and Claudie, 1951, 239359 (Box 12)
  - Published works: Claudie's Kinfolk, 1951, 239358 (Box 12)
  - Subseries A: Articles, 239353
    - "Communications Overkill," Proceedings Philosophical Society of Texas, 1968, 239357 (Box 12)
    - "Billingsley's Bondage," Texas Bar Journal, Vol. 24, no. 9, Oct. 22, 1961, 239356 (Box 12)
    - "Why Texans are That Way," Texas Adventures, Vol. I, no. 1, Oct. 1958, 239355 (Box 12)
    - "Oil and Trouble," review of Mikesell & Chenery's Arabian Oil, Saturday Review of Literature, May 14, 1949, 239354 (Box 12)
  - Subseries B: The Atlantic Monthly, 239336
    - "The Revival," Vol. 183, no. 6, June 1949, 239352 (Box 12)
    - "The Tunnel of Love," Vol. 184, no. 4, Oct. 1949, 239351 (Box 12)
    - "Never Start a Rumor," Vol. 186, no. 2, Aug. 1950, 239350 (Box 12)
    - "Horace Q. Ball for Governor," Vol. 186, no. 5, Nov. 1950, 239349 (Box 12)
    - "The Weather Prophet," Vol. 187, no. 1, Jan. 1951, 239348 (Box 12)
    - "The Receiver," Vol. 187, no. 3, March 19151, 239347 (Box 12)
    - "Claudie's Cosmic Vibrations," Vol. 188, no. 4, Oct. 1951, 239346 (Box 12)
    - "The Delegates," Vol. 192, no.1, July 1953, 239345 (Box 12)
    - "A Buffalo Named Woodrow," Vol. 193, no. 3, March 1954, 239344 (Box 12)
    - "Portrait of a Poker Player," Vol. 194, no. 6, Dec. 1954, 239343 (Box 12)
    - "Billingsley's Bird Dog," Vol. 196, no. 6, Dec. 1955, 239342 (Box 12)
    - "The President and National Security," Vol. 197, no. 1, Jan. 1956, 239341 (Box 12)
    - "The Meanest Man in Washington County," Vol. 198, no. 3, Sept. 1956, 239340 (Box 12)
    - "Chairman Billingsley," Vol. 199, no. 1, Jan. 1957, 239339 (Box 12)
    - "The Compleat Billingsley," Vol. 202, no. 5, Nov. 1958, 239338 (Box 12)
    - "Indeed There is a Mrs. Billingsley," Vol. 208, no. 3, Sept. 1961, 239337 (Box 12)
  - Subseries C: Southwest Review, 239332
    - "Forty Years of Firewood," Vol. XXXVI, no. 4, Autumn 1951, 239335 (Box 12)
    - "The Promised Land," Vol. XXXIX, no. 4, Summer 1954, 239334 (Box 12)
    - "From Law to Literature," Vol. XL, no. 3, Summer 1955, 239333 (Box 12)
  - Subseries D: Collier's, 239322
    - "The Windmill Fixers," Vol. 126, no. 9, Aug. 26, 1950, 239331 (Box 12)
    - "The Auction," Vol. 127, no. 4, Jan. 27, 1951, 239330 (Box 12)
    - "A Funny Thing About Treasure," Vol. 128, no. 13, Sept. 29, 1951, 239329 (Box 12)
    - "A Quilt for Claudie," Vol. 128, no. 26, Dec. 29, 1951, 239328 (Box 12)
    - "Born to Pick Cotton," Vol. 130, no. 13, Sept. 27, 1952, 239327 (Box 12)
    - "Claudie's Fickle Heart," Vol. 132, no. 2, July 11, 1953, 239326 (Box 12)
    - "Dividing Claudie's Rich Aunt," Vol. 134, no. 2, July 23, 1954, 239325 (Box 12)
    - "The Locked Jewel Case," Vol. 134, no. 9, Oct. 29, 1954, 239324 (Box 12)
    - "Claudie, Friend of Phlox," Vol. 138, no. 5, Aug. 31, 1956, 239323 (Box 12)
  - Subseries E: Politik und Zeitgeschichte, 239320
    - "Der Prasident und die Sicherheit des Landes," BXIX/56, May 9, 1956 (Translation of "The President and National Security," The Atlantic Monthly, Vol. 197, no. 1, Jan. 1956), 239321 (Box 12)